<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Creating an EMF-IncQuery Project">
   <intro href="http://viatra.inf.mit.bme.hu/incquery/new/examples/school">
      <description>
         Creating an EMF-IncQuery project requires the existence of an EMF project which contains the <b>domain model in Ecore format</b>. This cheat sheet relies on the School example from the EMF-IncQuery website, for demonstration purposes (click the ? for more details). After completing this sheet, you will have a fully functional EMF-IncQuery plug-in project with a simple sample query.
      </description>
   </intro>
   <item
         href="/org.eclipse.emf.doc/tutorials/clibmod/clibmod.html"
         skip="true"
         title="Importing the School example EMF project">
      <description>
         In this step, we import an example EMF project with a simple domain model. If you are unfamiliar with EMF, you should read the help by pressing the ? icon at the right of the section title. If you already have an EMF project with a domain model, you can skip this section. In that case the query patterns in later steps must be adjusted for your domain model.
<br/> <br/>
To create the example EMF metamodel, you may either import the domain project (<b>school</b>) from the git repository on the website, or perform the following steps:<br/><br/>
(1) Create an <b>Empty EMF Project</b>, setting <b>school</b> as the project name.<br/><br/>
(2) Create an <b>Ecore Diagram</b> named <b>school.ecore</b> inside the model folder.<br/><br/>
(3) Draw the domain model according to the metamodel diagram as shown on http://viatra.inf.mit.bme.hu/incquery/new/examples/school. Save the diagram. <br/><br/>
(4) Create an <b>EMF Generator Model</b> named school.genmodel from the school.ecore file.<br/><br/>
(5) Open the genmodel, and <b>Generate Model Code</b> since it is a requirement of IncQuery. For demonstrational purposes also <b>Generate Edit Code</b> and <b>Generate Editor Code</b>.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Initializing the EMF-IncQuery project"
         dialog="true">
      <description>
         
      </description>
      <subitem label="Issue: File | New | Project | EMF-IncQuery | EMF-IncQuery Project">
         <command
               required="false"
               serialization="org.eclipse.ui.newWizard(newWizardId=org.eclipse.viatra2.emf.incquery.gui.newproject)"/>
      </subitem>
      <subitem label="Give a name to the project (e.g. school.incquery), then press Next."></subitem>
      <subitem label="On the second wizard page, add a reference to the school.genmodel Generator Model by pushing Add and browsing to the school.genmodel file in the school project. Click on Finish to proceed."></subitem>
   </item>
   
</cheatsheet>
